[Music]
[Applause]
I got hired by the Library of Congress
to buy their some of their Buddhist
books Asian books and for a year and so
I went there to find out what I'm
supposed to do and I walked into the
director's office and he looked at me
and he said do the necessary and they
said goodbye it's a nice do the
necessary for meditation all right let's
go
we're gonna do four parts of the Lions
dancing day and then tomorrow we'll do
five and you graduated then it's up to
you okay so today we'll add the fourth
round okay I'm gonna do it in two parts
because it's gonna be too long for you
okay we'll take a break halfway and then
but you know when you do it by yourself
you feel like it's too much and you're
tired and you finished with the llama
and all that and you're like why do I
have to do more than eight dub star and
in a yoga pose you know we had this yoga
teacher Dharma Mitra who is amazing and
he's 70 something 80 and he does a
headstand with no arms and so anyway
when you go to his class he gets you in
the pose you know and you're shaking he
says all shaking is good shake he's good
because you're building when you're
shaking you're getting stronger okay and
then again he'll say just hold it one
more one more second you know just one
more second just one more second you
know and you're like
you know so his idea which I think it's
true is that when you're tired and when
you're shaking is when you get stronger
okay so I guess that's why Buddha added
step four in step five
okay you're supposed to get the stronger
it you feel like you don't want to do it
you feel like oh that's enough I don't
want to do this crystal sugar crystal
stuff but that's when you build up your
endurance okay and your meditation gets
stronger when you're tired if you do it
when you're tired okay but we're gonna
take a break okay all right here we go
so please come to the sound in the room
it could be the air conditioner at home
you probably have garbage trucks or kids
in traffic if you have a refrigerator
near your meditation space that's very
good for Alliance dance if you're not
doing the Alliance dance you might want
to unplug your refrigerator and don't
forget to plug it back in
we'll stay on the sound rest your mind
on the sound like you are resting your
head on a pillow
now let's go to our heartbeat watch your
heartbeat from the outside if you're in
a very quiet place you can hear the
heartbeat in your ears
rest your mind on the heartbeat don't
struggle don't look for it just rest
your mind on the heartbeat
now go inside the heart and feel the
walls beating around you a little bit
quieter and it's not dark and it's not
small
it's nice beautiful meditation room I'd
like to put lots of cushions lots of
windows and the sunlight is coming in
and the air inside is very very fresh
like a mountain air like the air at
Diamond Mountain
down let's expand that room almost like
a penthouse on top of a building and we
go into a inner room inside the
apartment so not on the outside walls
but there's an inner room like the core
up the heart step inside
even more quiet place close the door you
can still feel the outer walls of the
penthouse are beating but it seems far
away
now inside that room there's a small
table next to you and on the table is a
small pot of sugar and you reach in with
your finger and you pull down on the tip
of your finger there's a few sugar
crystals choose one of them and then
decide you'd like to put your mind in a
more quiet place and put your mind
inside that crystal it's kind of a
difficult to squeeze in but when you get
inside you're surprised to find there's
another beautiful room inside the inside
room and extremely quiet in the center
of the center of the heart and meditate
inside the sugar crystal which from the
inside is a very elegant meditation room
with lots of sunlight
now it's starting to expand the mine and
stay in shine inside the sugar crystal
and imagine the ocean I'm very very wine
if you like you can imagine a drop of
water dropping in the middle of the
ocean and then the ripples go out and
out and out you can follow those ripples
going out towards the edge of the earth
in the deep deep blue sea
dark blue very Placid very peaceful
ocean and you can follow those ripples
going out to the edges I like to think
of a place that I actually used to go to
for surfing and I get in the water and I
go out on the third floor and then I
look at the horizon and think of it very
far away
you might try the exhaling special
exhale we're about halfway through and
it's helpful to get any extra air out of
your lungs so when when you finish your
exhale then very gently push out a
little bit more air and your lower
stomach will tighten that will help you
sit straight and you won't feel so tight
now let's add the sky endless light blue
sky to the edges of the earth and up far
high higher and higher endless lifeless
sky let your mind relax and expand and
make it very very spacious
now let's turn off our mind try to stop
thinking and if thoughts come up
recognize it and push them away
now let's do the same thing but let's go
deeper to the center of the turned off
mine and if thoughts flow by our
memories images just let them go don't
engage with them stay in the core the
silent core of the mine
now we're ready to start the meditation
everything before that is just kind of
warming up the mind getting the mind
ready and now we'll choose a meditation
object and then we'll start the
meditation so our meditations start with
an object it's actually impossible for
the mind not to have an object so think
of one of your sweet teachers in this
night and ask them to come and sit in
front of you meditate together
it's traditional to choose the teacher
from the sweetest day you ever spent
together not maybe not
not a day when you had a hard time or
something but it's traditional to pick a
special day that you had together and
bring this most beautiful version of
your teacher
and then think of some quality about
them that you really like
that colonies coming from you from seeds
in your mind it's actually a reflection
of who you are it's a beautiful part of
you and then go back in your past lives
imagined past life be very free feel
free to go to any place any time any
country any body human animal any sex
male or female go back and make a story
about what you did in that different
place and time to plant the seeds to see
this beautiful quality in your teacher
you created that teacher by being kind
in the past so go back and enjoy make a
beautiful story don't be shy you deserve
it you created that quality and make a
very glorious and sweet history of the
planting of this teacher and their best
quality we'll spend a little bit longer
here
then please come back to this room with
your teacher sitting with your teacher
and spend a just a one or two more
minutes thinking about this beautiful
quality now you see it in a different
way you see that that you really helped
to create it and we'll spend a few
minutes there and then we'll take a
break
and slowly open your eyes take a stretch
any questions
misssara me
[Applause]
Thank You brains just one I'm I
recognized this morning like something
clicked for me that I've been trying to
do this meditation as if each stage is
happening to me right now and my my
checker goes no it's not no nothing's
changed it feels the same and so I've
been really resistant but today I set it
in front of me like there is a me that's
doing it as separate me and that me
except for the distraction was I'm gonna
ask this question that me it can very
easily go through each of these stages
enjoy staying there it is it the same to
run the story versus do it I think we're
always doing that anyway maybe I know
what you I think I know what you mean
and I think I think we're always kind of
watching me right in the meditation so
you're just putting it kind of in front
of you but I think we're always doing it
in a reflective way anyway but I think
it'd be a fun exercise to try it that
way yeah you can be cool other question
Thank You Krishna my question is about
the stage where we go into how do you
tell someone's from Canada there are
lots of boots my question is about is
that correct
when we go into stopping our mind my
mind my meditation goes from light to
dark at that point and I'm wondering if
like maybe I'm supposed to still stay in
the light because it anyway that that's
part of it and the other part of the
question is when I'm not like stopping
the mind I am still very aware of sounds
especially if I don't have my earplugs
in I am aware of a sounds so my mind is
not stopping I am aware of the fact that
I am working it to stop the mind so all
of those things makes me aware that I
have not stopped the mind is there a
method or a trick or some strategy that
I could use yeah good question so two
questions I get that dark feeling when I
go inside the heart at the very
beginning like it sells its a GUI and
it's dark you know it's all like messy
wet and and it's dark so I think what
you're talking about is more of an
emotional
it feels dark to stop the mind
altogether in the text which by the way
I said I would give you the technical
text today but I'm gonna get give it to
you tomorrow because that I couldn't
finish the homework yesterday but I'll
give it to you tomorrow if I remember in
the text it's kind of they often talk
about and feeling anesthetized like when
the dentist gives you a shot and then
you can't feel anything and they say
during this process you feel like that
like someone has given you a shot of
anesthetic and you can't feel anything
and you're just dull down so yeah I
think it could get a little dark like
that and we're gonna talk about it today
or tomorrow and the garden is going to
talk
whether you can actually turn the mine
off and it's not possible the mind is
called
guilt in the name of the mind is dition
that's which holds the object so it's
actually impossible to turn the mind on
so we're just kind of pretending to turn
the mind off and don't get too
frustrated because you can't but you
just pretend that you did and you
pretend you're sort of like in a deep
sleep or anesthetized and you're not as
aware of outside objects like that it's
it's it's not possible to turn off the
mind and in many mistaken systems of
meditation they try to turn off the mind
and they think this is a goal and the
karmic result of that trying to uh Nesta
ties your mind trying not to feel
anything on the karmic result if you
just do that it's an interesting you get
forgetful you become forgetful you lose
your keys you lose your phone you can't
remember that you promise to cover
something in the class stuff like that
so yeah don't if you can't turn off your
mind just try to slow it down and just
try to make it quieter and try to
imagine turning off your mind if things
get dark that's why we do the golden
room meditation and that's a very
traditional way of presenting darkness
and it's called Noah and and it's a
difficult thing normally it's listed as
a antidote for Chinua for dull dull mind
and the text just says think of
something bright
you know like fill the room with
sunlight
look at the stars in your mind okay and
and it prevents this emotional darkness
feeling of darkness while you're turning
the mind off so you can bring up some
kind of Noah in your mind some kind of
light in your mind as you turn the mind
on what's the traditional antidote if it
gets worse if your if your dullness gets
worse it's part of your faces is the
extreme so here is thinking of something
bright
you know like sunlight and here is
standing up and putting what about
what's in the middle think of something
that makes you happy okay think of
something that goes that went well in
your life you know many years ago
something went well and think of some
happy moment in your life that's a kind
of an emergency technique to prevent
darkness and so there's three levels
first you think of something bright like
spring sunlight into the picture I like
to soft sunlight and like not not these
overhead bright lines or something like
that and then if that doesn't work you
can detour to something that made you
very happy in the past like your mother
it's a good example she came here she
she was a very beautiful person and and
I think of her for a while and then go
back to the to the turning the mind off
but but don't get frustrated if you
can't turn the mind off and it seems
like the harder you try the louder it
talks so just gently try to turn the
mind off and one more question and we'll
take a break
thank you can you shut up for teaching I
would consume it FME he was head
buta okay the vanity is better line
stands meditation and if Raghav K
treatments were in team part Votto in
the sugarcane house kissed intelligent
man takes off mocks I have a question a
line dance on the part where in the
sugar crystal and then you expand
everything as you walk into the sugar
crystal you have a filler teaching
phonemic heard about this allow intense
I have heard many teachings from you
about the landings but Jesus mal has to
meet a hot day pneumatic contact traffic
fragmented
so Cesana said that in the past when you
did the lion dance and that part you
explained it yourself through the
universe and you sometimes even greeted
other people meditating in other worlds
and this time this is not happening
anymore and the question from Susannah
is there a specific reason for that or
when I taught it in earlier sessions we
expanded to the whole sky and then we
spend it to outer space and while we
were that's because I read a lot of
science fiction and as you're expanding
you hit other planets and of course
there are people doing lions dance right
now in other planets not one or two
there are countless planets so there are
countless groups like us doing lion
stands right now and they even look like
you you see there's one chance out of a
million that Vivian is in that group
looks just like Vivian and there's two
chances out of a million then there's
also and then there's you know a small
small chance that there's a group just
like this and there's a diamond mountain
another diamond all the roads are
finished in that diamond mountain
and so I like to imagine that my mind is
kind of overlapping with someone else's
doing line stands their mind is
expanding my mind is expanding and I
like to meet them halfway hi
you're doing lights dance - yeah yeah do
that that's fun that's for sure that's
fun yeah I I'm trying to get the ocean
to help you expand your mind when you
get to the sky but if you have the power
to go further that's great that's fine
no problem
very good okay let's take a peep you
break and come back when you hear the
belt
okay try not to talk too much if you can
[Music]
okay let's finish the Lions Den okay so
cough as much as you can blow your nose
anybody you're always welcome to record
it and use it at home especially
starting tomorrow we'll do all five
rounds
hmm
I think I hear my nephew Nikolas
some people say grandnephews now correct
yeah okay ready
let's go
so we were sitting with our llama or any
other teacher in your life focus on that
quality about them we talked about the
dependent origination of that colony
that it came from the seeds in my mind
from something beautiful I did in the
past but now let's look at the emptiness
of that quality so I like to play a
little game with my teacher I said could
you please sit to the side just sit off
to the side a little bit in Buddhism is
kind of touchy to tell your teacher to
do anything so you have to be super
respectful me I need to do an emptiness
meditation we call cessation meditation
same thing and I need to bring the other
Lama in front of me which is the fake
one
Giada the one who is not real and I need
to focus on this one for just a minute
or two so bring back effect Lama
the real Lama probably went for coffee
or something and now there's this
teacher in front of me you can do this
two ways you can think about the quality
they have in my case today it's a kind
of very peaceful nature of the law
and you can think about you can try to
remember how you used to see that
quality as if it were inside the teacher
and showing out on the outside you can
do it that way I for me if I'm trying to
think about the self existence of my
teacher and the Guardian has 27 ways
right the Guardian is going to teach us
27 different examinations of a fake Lama
but I I like to think about how I first
met them it was one of it was the most
important day of my life and I like to
think about how did I however I always
thought about that moment and I can
trace threads causes you know I can say
this teacher lived in a house near not
not so close but in the same city and I
never met them I never saw them I didn't
know about them and then one day and
they got in a car and they came to my
house and they got out of the car I
remember them getting out of the car and
seeing them for the first time and I
remember them coming to the door of my
house and I remember having dinner
together
so that's how I imagine the events that
led up to meeting my teacher for the
first time in this life but that's a
fake teacher that's not the real one the
real one came from seeds in my mind
their house on the other side of the
city was created by seeds in my mind
their car was created by seeds in my
mind the the highway they drove on was
created by seeds in my mind the opening
of the door of their car was created by
seeds in my mind and approaching me at
the door of my house getting bigger and
bigger as they crossed the lawn front
lawn those are all seeds sending
pictures so trying to get in touch right
now with a fake teacher oh the road was
built by the government the car was
bought by her mother you know the door
opened because she put her hand on the
handle and tried to imagine how you
usually think about how you met your
teacher this is a thing
if you keep thinking like that you will
lose them because you won't plant the
seeds you need to keep them
you can add that quality oh it was
inside them in their house before they
came to my house they brought that
beautiful quality wood with them in the
car that's all fake
now that's the fake llama to go away
respectfully and bring back the real
Lama to sit in front of you
and one more time think about where they
came from and where this beauty in them
came from and you can do a little coffee
meditation you can be super happy that
you created this beautiful thing most
beautiful thing in your life yesterday
someone showed me their real app it was
called rainbow turtle and it was very
beautiful about appreciating where the
beauty in their life is coming from I
said why you call it turtle they said oh
you can carry this beautiful home with
you everywhere you go you can always
find beautiful things and think about
how they're coming from good things you
did
and let's go back down
we'll start with turning off the mind
from the center of the mine and letting
other thoughts fall around just outside
that inner core so there's an inner core
of silence and thoughts are sort of
floating around outside but we don't
watch them we don't think about them we
stay quiet in the middle of the mine
turned off
going down we I'd like to increase the
decrease their breath by hot so we'll go
down a little faster than we went up so
come to stopping your mind but you're
staying aware of the thoughts it's a
little bit less quiet to fight the four
thoughts there come up
let's come back to the sky wide spacious
open mind beautiful new color just like
diamond mountain sky
Lucy brought fast why deep stretching to
the edges of the horizon
you sugar crystal super quiet single
point
in their chamber of the mind of the
heart
and then inside the heart walls are
beating sunlight
and then watching your heart back inside
your body
now we're going to go back up this is
Round four
and we're going to add something new
which is called panko inside the mine
Stan's Belgaum means we're going to
insert a short emptiness meditation
between each of the eight levels as we
go up and this is to strengthen the
meditation muscle so we're going to skip
from just sort of exercising in mental
quiet they were going to skip to
emptiness and then we'll come back to
mental quiet and we'll work our way up
to level eight this way with velcome
we're tired
the meditation mind is tired we've been
sitting now almost two hours today and
it'll be a little harder and that's okay
it's like shaking during yoga if you
push yourself when it's hard you get
stronger
so go back to the quality of your
teacher try to remember the quality
and realize it came from you and it's
not coming from inside of them
that means you can always keep it you
can always enjoy it
now go inside your heart find some quiet
and don't think about the llama just
take a break
meditation break inside the heart relax
have quiet
come back to your llama remember the
beautiful quality try to remember where
did it come from what was that thing I
did in my past night
come back to the inner core of the heart
the walls of the heart are beating at a
distance take a rest in the quiet inside
the inside of the heart lots of sunlight
maybe you can lay down in the sunlight
take a rest
remember the exhaling trick when you're
tired maybe your chest is getting a
little bit tight extra exhale
come back to the lama think about how
this quality is not coming from inside
of them you created it and you can keep
it going it's up to you if you love my
changes that's also coming from you
sugar crystal take a rest in the sugar
crystal quiet single point like a laser
beam like the point of a laser beam
take a rest
in the quiet
exhale
come back to the number
try to think of things you'd like to do
today see what you'd like to plant to
keep this quality in your teacher if
it's patience that they had think about
situations today when you might be
patient
come back to the ocean relax quiet
expensive
come back to the teacher I so appreciate
this good quality in you maybe you can
tell them
appreciate them
come to the sky rest in the blue sky
packed a llama
silent appreciate
turn off the mine
block any thought
back to the teacher oh I must be it I
must have some good part of me if I can
see this person there must be some
goodness in me
back to the mind turn off to my take a
rest let the thoughts thought through
ignore them
back to the teacher you can in your mind
join your palms in front of your chest
bowed to them thank you for being in my
life
with your beautiful qualities
and then three long excels
and then you can smell they open your
eyes take a stretch yeah you did level
four you did a fourth around any
questions
thank you guys effort our genus in the
quality that I choose from my llama is
why i steam a llama as a good meditator
and I saw a child who was living like
very far away from the crowd with their
parents and he was spending a lot of
time playing alone he was observing the
little animals
he was emerging like beautiful things
with people a perfect world but actually
he didn't choose to have this kind of
life he didn't choose to be alone he
didn't choose don't hurt other people he
was forcing by his past Karma and that's
what I see my llama has a good meditator
but my question is if we didn't we don't
choose what we were thinking now where
are we saying and what are we doing now
when actually we plan the new Karma
okay let me see if I got it right
so in Buddhism we're gonna talk about it
today or tomorrow there's two kinds of
causes I mean there are many Kazakh
kinds of causes but one way to divide
causes is direct causes and indirect
causes so for example in your class
today or tomorrow don't remember we'll
talk about a coffee cup and you know the
indirect cost was a person who made it
you know maybe five years ago that
person could even be dead now you see
that's we call Giga which means indirect
cost
and then there's a direct cost which
chin son brought it to me from the
kitchen you see
so they're both causes of the coffee cup
one happened a long time ago we can't
see it anymore but it but it made the
coffee cup and then the direct cost for
me was that someone brought it from the
kitchen so I think your question is like
the indirect cause of my llama being a
good meditator was that the child had
seeds in their mind that caused them to
be out alone and see animals and not to
hurt them and in the direct cause of my
lamas meditation was this child but the
causes that made the child's life happen
before the child right so those are
indirect causes for your lamas
meditation and then the child is the
direct cause for an enormous meditation
and I think your question is going this
way if if these old old causes if the
old cause create my teachers meditation
and the old old costs create the cause
of my teachers meditation then it seems
like it's going to be difficult to
change things you know I'm kind of is
their free will right do I have a choice
all right or it's my all my decisions
made by the boy the Karma that made the
boy see it like can I change my life is
it possible to change if everything is
caught in a big web of causes and even
my decision to change is coming from
cost then how can I improve you know
what can I do I like to tell a joke I
heard there was a scientific conference
in Europe probably Germany
and somebody said we have no choice but
to accept free will
[Laughter]
yeah it's true we are very caught it's
harder to change than we think because
it's not a decision you can make about
today you see like getting Michael likes
donors getting Mike I would like to
change that habit but it's not something
I can do in one day it comes from a
cause that came from accounts that come
from a cause they come from a cause
there's a thousand causes to eat a
doughnut and there's only one to not eat
a doughnut
and who's going to win but we are very
much caught up in Buddhism they say an
interesting thing okay as you learn if
you have the causes to be in this class
then you will learn a new idea which is
that things are coming from you okay you
will learn a new Nydia and that's super
true okay and there are other things in
your life are true some things are true
some things are not true
but the fact that things are coming from
you is super true so according to
Buddhism super true takes priority
okay and like if I have addiction we
taught we learned about addiction right
we had a two-week course about it if I
understand that this thing I'm addicted
to donut it's coming from me
that is so true super true that it's
more powerful than the old seeds of
addiction you see so there's true things
and they're super true things and
according to Buddhism when you meet
super true things like new gardeners
wisdom
they are more powerful than all those
past seeds
you see they they are like Superman
compared to Geshe Michael so they can
win they will win even a thousand to run
the super true thing will will win so
that's why we're working so hard on
unwisdom on the book wisdom because that
karma is it's like a atom bomb and it
can destroy all the past ones cool yeah
good question one more question if you
like one here hey thanks for the
teaching I have a question about the
last part of the meditation we are asked
to switch from Lama to the sky and that
can force me I understand why why we
switch back and forth okay it's called
belgaum pelo means alternating
meditation and if you really want to
know okay level three four five in the
scripture are called to go to go to gell
means over the top going over the top
coming back down tapa means the top part
of your skull and in sanskrit it's
cupola which came to be the word for cup
or coppola right Venga me probably the
same he sent me to a restaurant in
France within Coppola so well we're the
first two levels technically are the
main Lyons dance that's the first two
rounds technically are the main lines
dance three four five are called
to Gao and three and five are
alternating
sorry foreign fire so we will put
something between each number we will go
back and forth why do we do that and why
don't we even do this eight meditations
on the way up
why are we spending time on meditations
there's two reasons okay number one
oftentimes in Buddhism they will teach
you what's wrong so you don't do it you
see I mean so the first reason to do all
this like space meditation ocean
meditation it's a warning on the
cigarette package it says some people
call this meditation but it's not okay
and it will hurt you okay so so there's
a negative reason to do those
meditations is so you don't think those
are real meditation they're not okay
they're not meditation they're just sort
of warming up second positive reason is
mental flexibility it's called shinjang
search-engine shinjang means mental
flexibility and if you're gonna be a
good Buddhist you need mental
flexibility things are going well you
know for 10 minutes Popo hits you again
you know and then a buddhist needs a
mental flexibility you know you have to
okay new situation alright I'll take
care of it your wife suddenly gets angry
I didn't do anything and then you gotta
be flexible to be a good Buddhist then
in your meditation it'll be going very
very smooth and then suddenly you know
you start thinking about someone who
criticized you yesterday and then the
whole rest of the meditation or the
whole rest of the three-year retreat
it's about this person you know they
hurt me so much and I don't like this
person so we're practicing flexibility
of the mind a new situation comes up and
you flow with it you know you you bring
up a different antidote in your mind so
there's a I had I took a yoga class one
time my teacher my first yoga teacher
gave me good advice you travel along so
everywhere you travel look up on the
internet and go to any yoga class
don't even look what they're teaching
one time I made a big mistake I went to
a prenatal class in Hong Kong but I got
some good stretches but I I remember I
went to one class and they said go into
a tree pose verges on a-- and you know
stand on one leg and then the teacher
come around and push everybody a little
bit you know and then you know he try to
stay up you see and then the next class
they didn't do it but still you were
better your tree pose was better because
you're expecting someone - so you're
like you know so uh like that and we're
supposed we're trying to make the mind
stronger yeah
otherwise this meditation frankly it
seems too busy right like it's too busy
you know I just got used to it guys no
don't go back to the you know I just
appreciated man I'll go back to the sky
well
but life is like that life is like that
so we're sort of getting practiced for
life if you want to if you feel like
it's too scattered like your life is
already scattered I don't guess I don't
need 26 parts to in meditation then you
can stop don't stop on on the eighth
don't stop on the way if somebody asked
me yesterday you know
stopping my mind seems really attractive
and I kind of want to just stop there
and I'm like no you cannot stop on the
first eight floors okay that the
elevator should keep going okay
it won't help you there's no content
okay and so but if you want to stop on
the path line if you want to stop and do
a long coffee meditation on how cool you
are because your Lama is cool then
that's fine and if you never you know
and then your alarm clock goes off and
you have to go to work and you get stuck
in your past life that's okay okay just
do three breaths come out gracefully
we're gonna learn a nice way to exit it
the meditation probably tomorrow but
traditionally you bring the lama to your
heart and then you can go to work okay
so if you feel like stopping at one of
the important parts and you don't want
to do all this pail gum you know you
need some peace today and you don't need
more chaos then you're welcome to stop
and stay there okay all right we're
gonna go to the class